[Music]
this program is brought to you by
stanford university
what omega is too you see that oh omega
big omega
yes
yeah
um
right
okay so peop you asked me what omega is
and
omega is an important quantity so let's
uh let's discuss it
um
you go back to the friedman robertson
walker equations
and those have the form
a dot over a
squared
we know about that and on the right hand
side
we have various things
we could have a vacuum energy
let's talk about
today
or at least for an era
well after
the
radiation-dominated era ended at the
time
which includes the present today
when the equation of state i'll just
wait a minute
oh wait a minute
all right
so
somebody asked me what capital omega now
there are
there are several capital omegas
incidentally
one of them simply represents the sphere
the two sphere or the three sphere
that's another that's a different omega
in cosmology there is another omega
which has to do with the
percentage
of matter or the percentage of energy in
different forms that come in different
forms
okay so let's
the percentage of the energy that goes
on the right-hand side
of the expansion equation the
friedman-robertson-walker equation the
left-hand side of course is the hubble
constant or the hubble parameter squared
the right-hand side can contain first of
all
a vacuum energy let's see it's not
called we shouldn't call it lambda rho
naught eight pi g
8 pi g over 3
times the vacuum energy
then
if we're talking about the era
uh which includes today
when radiation was not very important
and which mostly the energy density of
the universe apart from the vacuum
energy is dominated by ordinary
non-relativistic slowly moving
objects such as galaxies
then there's another term in here
which is
uh
let's say
row
matter
it also multiplies the 8 pi g over 3. so
let's put a bracket around it
the vacuum
energy the part which doesn't change
with expansion
and that of course just to remind you
this part here
is some constant
let's call it m
divided by a cubed so it dilutes with
expansion
there might also be a radiation part but
let's ignore it it's very very small
after the period
when the sun when the universe was very
very hot
when it cooled below the temperature of
the sun let's say
radiation was not so important
and
the matter part of the energy density
was the important
part and let's see is there anything
we're missing
yeah we're missing
plus one over or plus
k
or minus k
over a squared
that's the curvature part
that's the part which is um k equals
plus one
for a positively curved universe k
equals minus one for a negatively curved
universe and k equals zero for a uh
for a flat universe
let's uh mostly concentrate on
for the moment on the flat universe
then all omega is
is it's the fraction of energy
well
let's put it this way yeah
it's just a fraction of energy carried
by the different components
okay
um
it must add up to one
for the simple reason that uh
sorry
i'm saying it not quite right
i'm saying not quite right
all right
[Music]
what i want to do is get rid of this and
put it over on the other side
uh
3 over 8 pi g
let's get rid of it over here
and let's forget this for the moment
now um
these two
have to add up to this this is the
square of the hubble constant they've
got to add up to this but not if k is
anything is either plus one or minus one
if k is plus one or minus one they don't
quite have to add up
to the left hand side here
the thing to do yeah to understand this
thing to do is to divide this equation
by what's on the left-hand side let's
just simplify it and call it hubble
squared this is the 8 pi 3 over g but
let's ignore that for the sake of
argument for here it's just hubble
squared times a number
and that's equal to the sum of three
terms here's the the way to think about
it the sum of three terms rho naught
plus row matter
minus k over
a squared
and this is either plus 1 over a squared
or minus 1 over a squared or whichever
and then divide it by hubble squared
divided by hubble squared 1
divided by hubble squared
these things have to add up to one
that's just uh the trivial i just
divided by the left hand side of the
equation to get one here
all right but notice that's not the only
thing we could say we can say if k is
equal to zero
these two things have to add up to one
the
energy density in the vacuum
together with the energy density and
matter must add up to one
otherwise
space can't be flat
now first of all
um
since rho naught and rho matter
vary differently with time
there's no way that this can be constant
so the only way you can have it add up
to one is if row matter over h squared
uh if as if there's no um
h were constant but h is not constant h
is not constant in general and since h
is not constant in general there's
really no reason
why
this cannot add up to one in general if
h is varying with time so because h
varies with time rho naught over row
mata over h squared could add up to one
but it can only add up to one
if k is equal to zero that's what the
equations tell you that if rho naught
plus row matter over h squared add up to
one and what do you do you measure
the different components of the energy
you add them up
you divide by the observed hubble
constant squared
and here's a prediction if space is flat
if this is not important
then these have to add up to one
the energy density
or the vacuum energy density plus the
matter energy density divided by the
square of the observed hubble constant
must add up to one
now these things this is called omega
this is called omega and the first term
here is called omega 0 or sometimes
omega vacuum or sometimes omega lambda
to stand for cosmological constant
and the second term here
is just called omega matter
rho divided by h squared is called omega
okay
now first conclusion is if space is
flat omega naught plus omega m must add
up to one
so in that sense
if k is equal to zero
omega naught and omega matter are simply
the fraction of energy
carried by either vacuum energy or
matter energy that's what they are
they can change with time but they have
to change with time in such a way as to
add up to one
but if on the other hand space is curved
if space is curved then we can put on
the right hand side 1 plus k over a
over
a squared h squared
and then the sums of the omegas do not
have to exactly add up to one
okay
adding them up and then let me remind
you what this means
you first measure to the best of your
ability
extra astronomically in various ways
you measure the vacuum energy you
measure the matter energy and you divide
it by hubble squared the sum
the sum may or may not add up to one
if it adds up to one that's an
indication that space is flat so when
people say space is flat
it implies that the sum of these two
have to add up to one and in that case
they really are just the fraction of
energy
carried by matter and by vacuum okay
if these two don't quite add up to one
for example if they add up to something
bigger than one
that says that k is positive
it implies that the universe must be
positively curved so if you measure
hubble and you measure rho
and the ratio is bigger than one
then space must be positively curved if
it's less than one then k must be
negative and space must be negatively
curved so this is what omega is omega
is a measure yeah
does that include dark matter yes it
includes dark matter and anything else
besides
dark matter and regular
well yeah well we could we could add in
here row radiation but it's such a small
fraction that it doesn't that it doesn't
matter so in practice it's just matter
and uh vacuum
yeah is there some some measure of dark
energy other than the holocaust
the hubble constant itself
is not a measure of dark energy it's the
way that the hubble constant changes
with time
the fact that it doesn't seem to be
changing with time
uh is which is the indication
of
dark matter
dark energy dark energy
yeah
the fact that the change the time rate
of change of the hubble constant is
decreased which is the same thing as
saying that that we're on this branch of
exponential expansion
in other words
if a dot over a is becoming constant
that's equivalent to saying a is
exponentially increasing
so the observed apparent tendency toward
exponential increase
is the measurement of is the direct
evidence for rho naught
okay
but isn't that
the same thing as
indicate i mean
how is that separate from age
well
okay
it's not
it's not you're asking uh
observationally how do you tell the
difference
observationally what you actually
measure is k
what you actually measure is k and k
tells you what rho naught is
observationally you measure the fact
geometry geometrically we haven't had a
chance to get into this but
geometrically you measure the fact that
on large scale space is flat
that tells you that k is equal to zero
once you know k is equal to zero
uh
and you have also measured the matter
energy
then you know what rho naught has to be
given now that you know what ronald is
you can then predict the way the
universe expands with time
you find out that it's not zero and it
says that it's accelerated
so there is a predictive there is a
prediction in there
from the fact that space looks flat
it tells you that rho naught
or that
yeah
this you measure that's
you measure this by measuring
the ordinary
material in the universe that you can
see
plus the part that you can't see
which is the dark matter which you
measure gravitationally by the orbits of
uh stars around galaxies
yeah that's right we have three
different several different ways to
measure this
several ways to measure this they're
both measured
and
they add up to something close to one
sorry yes they add up to something
they add up to something we also measure
the hubble constant
and it all adds up but on top of that
the the measurement of the curvature
itself
is equal to zero
so you solve for row zero yeah so we
have some cross checks there are various
cross checks
and
the cross checks involve the
acceleration of the universe which tells
us that
the direct measurement of matter and uh
and dark matter which tells us that
the direct measure of the hubble
constant which just looks out the
different distant galaxies and tells you
how fast they're moving
indeed
they add up to about one and that tells
us that space ought to be flat
and then you measure the curvature of
space
by triangulating it and you find that
it's flat
okay to a good approximation
uh
so those are the pieces of evidence
that are telling us that however we got
that way we don't know but space is very
very flat to
a couple of percent
why is it so flat
well
the theory
is that it inflated
being flat just means it's very big it's
very big and very smooth very big and
very smooth and very homogeneous
on scales how big on scales of billions
of light years on scales of billions of
light years in fact really tens of
billions of light years it's very flat
very homogeneous
how did it get wet that way the spec the
speculation or the conjecture and by now
it's more than a conjecture there's good
empirical evidence for it
that the universe
underwent a very early period
before
what we normally call a big bang
the universe underwent a period of
exponential expansion
and that exponential expansion just
stretched it out
stretched it out so much that it
appeared very very flat
now you can overdo a good thing
the universe is very flat
and at the time of the big bang it was
very smooth
but if it were perfectly smooth if it
had been perfectly smooth
then there would be no way
for structure to form a perfectly smooth
universe one which is perfectly
symmetric will stay perfectly symmetric
the equations of gravity and so forth
will not create lumpiness out of perfect
smoothness
and so we know that the universe wasn't
perfectly smooth
and
if we trace backward from the current
knowledge of galaxies and the current
knowledge of the of the degree to which
the universe is not homogeneous if we
trace that backward
we find out that at the time
when the universe
first became transparent
at the time that radiation decoupled
from matter and so forth the time that
we normally call a big bang
there was something like about one a one
part and ten to the fifth
anisotropy and inhomogeneity that means
if we were to have plotted at that time
the energy density or mass density as a
function of position
we would have found that it's very very
constant
almost perfectly flat
but and of course i can't draw this on
the blackboard
uh with about one part and ten to the
fifth there was a bit of wiggliness in
it
wiggliness in it at different scales
that wiggliness
now that's much
much smaller
than the current uh now by now
stuff is concentrated into galaxies
and it's highly
anisotropic in homogeneity and
homogeneous on small scales
so what happened
and this is something that we can follow
starting with this primordial little bit
of fluctuation where it came from
we go we have some ideas but where it
came from we don't ask at the moment we
say supposing it was there what happened
next
well
the little over densities these are
regions of over density
they were surrounded by regions of under
density let's draw those dotted and then
other regions of over density and so
forth
other regions of over density
the regions of over density gravitated
and pulled things toward them
in fact they pulled the matter
immediately in between these two these
two regions into the two regions
increased the over density
and increased the magnitude of the under
density
so
um it's a sort of self-reinforcing
feedback
that the more reflect the more and
in homogeneity you have the more gravity
will lead it to become yet more
inhomogeneous
this is different than the air in this
room
if we created a perturbation in the air
in the room a little wave-like
disturbance
that wave-like disturbance will
eventually disappear
it'll disappear it'll come to thermal
equilibrium
and the room will again become
homogeneous in its content of air
okay for example
so
gravity is different than other forces
it tends to lead to this instability
where a little over density
will increase itself in fact if you just
took a completely homogeneous universe
and put in just a little bit of over
density it would start sucking the
material from nearby and create an under
density
the under density would start to grow
and the over density would start to grow
and eventually the thing would collapse
and form perhaps a galaxy yeah why
didn't gravity do that before that
ah that's a good question okay
that's a good question that that is a
good question
why did it happen at the time that
radiation became unimportant compared to
the other all right
the reason has to do with pressure
remember we talked about
we talked about the relation between
pressure and energy density
i wrote it on the blackboard pressure
is equal to something called w w is just
a
just a parameter times the energy
density i think i call it epsilon does
anybody remember what i called it the
density of energy
well maybe row yeah we called it row
sure sure we did
okay so let's see how much you can
remember
okay for
radiation what is
w
ordinary radiation electromagnetic
radiation filling a room this room is
not filled with electromagnetic
radiation it's mainly filled with atoms
but black body radiation for black body
radiation
the pressure
this is not momentum it's pressure
anybody remember the formula
one third
all right the energy density was pretty
high
and therefore at that early time and
therefore there was a good deal of
pressure
what positive pressure does is it tends
to do exactly what happens in this room
positive pressure
tends to homogenize things
if there's positive pressure positive
pressure is good for homogenizing things
it pushes everything out and tends to
create a homogeneous background that's
in fact why the air in the room
is homogeneous the positive pressure now
what about
matter dominated oh let's before we do
that what about uh vacuum dominated
anybody remember vacuum dominated
yeah minus one but i just ask you that
to see if you remember
all right but what about what about
matter dominated
zero
no pressure at all
that means that uh if there was no
pressure whatever in this room
and there was no gravity let's start
with no pressure and no gravity if there
were no pressure in other words if the
air molecules exerted no pressure how
could that be what would it take for the
for the molecules to uh to have to exert
no pressure
they would have to have zero velocity
right zero velocity they'd be standing
perfectly still
obviously if they stand perfectly still
and you create a bit of inhomogeneity
it's just frozen in it doesn't do
anything
why because the molecules are standing
perfectly still p equals zero means
everything's standing still
ah
but now
add a little bit of gravity on top of
that
if we add a little bit of gravity on top
of that
then the standing still is not enough to
overcome the tendency of gravity to pull
things toward the center
so it's a kind of competition
gravity versus pressure
pressure keeps things from imploding
gravity
can overcome pressure if it's strong
enough and cause something to implode
now very simply
during the radiation dominated era the
pressure was so high
that it simply prevented
gravity from doing its work and causing
causing implosion
radiation pressure was very high
and it just prevented
it just prevented
lumps from forming in the same way that
it does in this room here
eventually the radiation pressure became
negligible
the pressure due to the motion of
galaxies motion of other things was also
negligible and gravity became the most
important part gravity became more
important than the pressure and at that
point stuff started to uh to contract
yeah so that was before the
don't you need a dissipation mechanism
to have yes
well
actually you need a dissipation
mechanism to cause the uh ordinary
baryonic matter to uh to collide not to
uh not to have the dark matter
create
halos
so the first thing that happened is the
dark matter
the fluctuations in the dark matter
and the fact that the pressure was so
small
started to create lumps of dark matter
now the dark matter created lumps and
the ordinary matter sort of followed
those lumps
but then the dissipative mechanisms
caused the the ordinary matter to start
to collect near the center of those
lumps and the dark matter didn't
dissipate so it just stayed there out
there as big halos
so you don't need dissipation
you don't need
i know what you're thinking
um
there's a form of dissipation in
cosmology which i was going to talk
about in a few minutes
there's a form of dissipation in
cosmology which doesn't have to do with
the normal things it has to do with
expansion
expansion creates its own kind of
dissipation
uh
and
the expansion replaced dissipation
yes since the dark matter is effectively
an ideal gas yeah
it's an ideal gas at zero temperature
would we still see it in its
original configuration
no was its original configuration
and gravity started it moving a little
bit gravity started it condensing into
lumps
well expansion eats up the the
i was going to talk a little bit about
the relationship between dissipation and
expansion and
we'll see it because we'll need it for
something else
but just in an expanding time dependent
universe
uh you don't need dissipation to slow
things down
so we'll come to it
was the dark matter did the dark matter
exist when there was nothing but energy
is dark matter what do you mean nothing
but energy all there ever is is energy
of various forms
you mean radiation energy
no it was there
yeah
in fact the um
there are two times scales which are
close to each other but not exactly the
same
there's the time scale
or the time
at which the universe became transparent
and there's a separate time scale which
is the time scale when
the matter energy density in other words
the non-relativistic dark matter that
energy density became larger than the uh
than the radiation energy
those are two crossover points
one of them is a place where cooled
enough for atoms to recombine
and the other is a place where the the
matter density in the dark matter
exceeded
the radiation pressure and allowed
allowed contraction to start happening
the contraction started happening a
little bit before
maybe a factor of 10 in time that this
sounds like that is a little bit uh on
the scale of these things
uh happened a little bit before
the universe became transparent so
unfortunately we can look back to it
uh a little bit before the universe was
maybe another factor of 10 smaller
uh
that
the gravity started to do its work on
the dark matter
if the dark matter hadn't been there and
it was only ordinary matter
then
the
start of the contracting phase not the
contraction of the universe but the
contraction of these lumps
would have happened about the same time
just more or less accidentally about the
same time
that the universe became transparent
and we might have been able to look back
and actually see it happening but uh we
can't
so it's the dark matter which provides
yeah one or two more questions and then
i want to uh yeah
uh what are the problems you've given us
is the elements greater than helium
the elements greater than helium
developed inside stars
for the most part
the reason i haven't talked about it
very much
is because it's not really considered to
a certain extent part of ordinary
cosmology
it happened too late it happened it's
really part of astrophysics it's really
part of the dynamics of stars
um almost
all of the heavy elements except for a
tiny tiny bit
which was produced uh during the big
bang you never say none i mean never say
never but during the big bang
virtually nothing but hydrogen and
helium were produced
oh yeah a bit of that that's a form of
hydrogen yeah right a bit of deuterium
hydrogen and helium
everything else was almost completely
negligible
although a little bit little trace bits
of it
the actual
current abundance of it was mainly made
during the stellar evolution in
thermonuclear processes
so
in some sense it's not considered part
of cosmology it's part of
part of astrophysics
that's probably taking a narrow view of
cosmology
in addition to the inhomogeneity
position there also had to be a little
emotions of the galaxies with that
angular event
oh they also had some angular momentum
yeah but that was just inherited
from uh from these fluctuations that
they started with
those density fluctuations but they also
had some motion there was also velocity
fluctuations density and velocity
and what we actually see in the sky
is temperature fluctuations across the
sky which are remnants of these uh
little bits of over density and under
density and also
a little bit of their motion
the motion of the gas at that time
either toward us away from us
also tended to produce some variation in
the apparent temperature on the sky
so let's just remember i mean we look
back
we look
way far out to the surface of last
scattering
and some of that surface of last
scattering is a little bit over dense
some of it is a little under dense
the over dense regions tend to look a
little bit hotter to us
no the overdense regions tend to look a
little bit colder to us excuse me
the reason is
because the over dense regions have a
little more mass they have a little more
gravity and because they have gravity
the photons that come from them
are somewhat red-shifted more than they
would be from the other regions
so from the over dense region where
gravity is a little bit stronger it's
pulling the photons back so we see
looking from here
the over dense regions the photons look
a little bit less energetic
from the underdense regions they look a
little bit
extra energetic but there's also another
thing going on this gas is in motion
some of the motion may be toward us or
away from us so there's also a bit of
doppler shift and the doppler shift also
things which are moving toward us look
hotter things which are moving away from
us look colder
all of this gets folded in
and it's complicated the difficult
numerical calculations
to start with a given initial condition
and to evaluate what uh you know what
what flows out of that
experts do that
and the conclusion
basic conclusion was at the time that
the universe became transparent or even
a little before that there was about one
part and ten to the fifth
variation
uh
in the
energy density of the universe so on the
one hand it was very very smooth
it
was also the universe is also known to
be very flat
so it appears as if it expanded a great
deal
but on the other hand if it had expanded
infinitely
you might have thought
that it would iron out these
variations here
so could it be that these variations are
due to the fact that it didn't grow
by an enormous amount
well i wish that were the case but it's
not the case
um these fluctuations are there because
of quantum mechanics they're quantum
they're remnants of quantum mechanics
and they would be there even if the
universe had expanded by an infinite
amount or in the
infinite of course is silly even if it
expanded by 10 to the 10 to the 10 to
the 10 to the 10th
that would not have erased these
fluctuations those fluctuations would
have been created anew
by quantum mechanics so i thought we
would talk about that a little bit
and get into a little bit
why
why it is
that people believe this crazy theory
that the universe exponentially expanded
and remember what it took
what's that who doesn't believe it
i don't know
there are from time to time people who
will put forward other ideas
and usually the excuses well it's just
another idea with uh to uh to provide a
straw man in other words a uh
a
foil yeah
right
i don't know anybody who doesn't believe
it that may be a bad sign that there's
too many people believing
uh too many believers
you know i have my friend bob page who
who is a um
a evangelical christian he's also a very
famous physicist and a great one and we
argue all the time about
whether such things as whether jesus can
be proved to be the son of god and so
forth
and one of his arguments is how could so
many people believe it if it weren't
true i mean
so maybe inflation is like that i don't
know
i don't think so i think there's some i
think there's some
spectacular empirical success of the
idea
but in order to tell you what that
empirical success is
i have to tell you a little bit more
about it
all right uh
let's remember the idea starts with the
existence of a scalar field and it's a
scalar field that has a potential energy
which is just a function of the field
strength all right so we have a phi
which is some scalar field
what it's doing there and how it comes
into the physics of particle physics and
so forth is unknown
it's some scalar field called phi and
it's there for no other purpose other
than to provide some vacuum energy
the vacuum energy or the energy of this
field it has one component which is just
due
to the usual
energy of an oscillating field like the
electromagnetic field
the electromagnetic field has energies
for two sources one comes from its time
dependence
that's the electric energy and the other
comes from its space dependence its
gradients and that's its magnetic energy
but this field has another form of
energy which is just potential energy
v can this be seen i'm writing with blue
on blue
no okay
how about pink on blue
v of phi
so the energy in this field if i wanted
to i could write it down and a lot of
many of you have done some of these
classes would recognize it there's a
term in the energy density which
contains time derivative squared there's
another term which contains spatial
derivatives squared
this is the energy density it's
conventional to put a factor of 2 in
there
so
vibration of the field that's this one
gives energy variation of the field in
space that's this one gives energy
density and then one more term
a potential energy
v of phi
and everybody will agree
that scalar fields typically do have
such potentials
an example would be the higgs field
which some of you may or may not know
about but that's one which we
empirically have good reason to believe
in
and that has a vfi so vfi is not an
unusual thing
or peculiar thing
but its shape is a little bit unusual
and contrived
contrived meaning to say that you'd have
to
maybe tune some parameters
vfi is a function of phi well there are
zillions of functions around most of
them are not very simple
one is a simple function phi is a simple
function phi squared is not too
complicated a function phi cubed is
pretty simple if you start adding things
like 1 plus 5 plus 5 squared you can
make some pretty complicated functions
uh
and so it is with vfi it's a complicated
looking function meaning to say it's not
the thing that you might have written
down on your first uh you know in your
first calculus examination
but nevertheless
it has to have a shape which looks
something like this it has to be fairly
flat
over some range over some range it has
to be fairly flat
not absolutely flat don't want it to be
absolutely flat you want to have a
little bit of a slope
a little bit of slope downward
and then at some critical value of phi
the bottom drops out
and it falls away like so
now it doesn't quite fall to zero
it falls to something very small though
and then plunk units in natural units
units or plunk units plunk units are
units
in which c is equal to one
that's not hard to think about
planck's constant is equal to one
and newton's constant or equal to one
those are called plonk units
the units in which the natural unit of
length is the planck length which is 10
to the minus 33 centimeters the natural
unit of time is 10 to the minus 42
seconds
and uh the natural unit of mass anybody
know what the planck mass is
how much
10 minus 5 grams
right so it's some units so some natural
units in which the most basic constants
of nature are equal to 1
this falls down to something very small
about 10 to the minus 123.
that's the vacuum energy today
up here it was larger it was still small
and plunk units
we know that it could not have been
large on the on the planck scale
it was perhaps
much much bigger than this but much much
smaller than planck
the universe started
what does it mean to say the universe
started over here
what does it mean to say with this is
not a place incidentally this is a value
of the field
what does it mean to say the universe
started at this point when i say started
i don't mean to say that it literally
started at that point i mean to say we
can trace it back to a certain starting
point
which was more or less like this and the
details of this incidentally are not
well known
this is more of a cartoon of a situation
whose details are really somewhat
unknown
but more or less like this what does it
mean to say the universe started at a
particular point on this plot well it
means to say that the universe started
with the field value being something
having some value
filling space
now it's not important
whether it varied from place to place at
this point
because what's going to happen is the
universe is going to expand so much
that wrinkles and phi will get
enormously stretched out
and the region where we sit
is deep in the interior of one of these
very stretched out regions
and so for practical purposes we might
as well assume
that after
a little while up here the universe
expanded by so much
that our part of it our patch of it and
perhaps much more than that was very
very ironed out
why did the universe expand so fast
well that's the robertson walker
equation or friedman robertson walker
equation
and vfi vfi incidentally is something
which does not
um
what's the word i'm looking for does not
dilute
so it's like vacuum energy
in fact the vfi was perfectly flat
it would it would be exactly the same as
a vacuum energy
if for some reason the universe just sat
at a point in other words if phi did not
change and it just sat there then the
value of the potential energy at that
point would be vacuum energy
so as long as this is pretty flat
the universe will be exponentially
expanding
with an exponential factor
with a hubble constant
which will be proportional
to the square root of this vacuum energy
the square root of v of phi
i'm leaving out eight pi's and that sort
of thing
let's just put proportional to the
hubble constant will expand
proportional to the square root of v of
phi
and the universe will exponentially
expand like e to the h t
that will continue
what is spy defined on what's the space
is it is the field on some version of
space time yeah
but what is
the field
what is that space
do we know anything about that space
time we don't have einstein's field
equations right oh yes we do
absolutely this is
that is einstein's field equation
yeah yeah
oh yes
yes yes this is einstein's field
equation
and if we wanted to simplify it or or
we would just write for rho naught plus
row matter we would just write v
v phi
for the energy density
that's good enough as long as phi is
slowly varying
what happens to these pieces of the
energy
well as long as
phi is moving slowly with time
this is not important
and as long as it's been stretched out
as long as things have been stretched
out a great deal
then the gradient of phi is small
so these are unimportant
and phi is the big thing in the energy
while you're up on the top here
then of course you eventually
slide down the shallow hill and talk
about the dynamics of that in a moment
you slide down this shallow hill
until you get to the edge and then plop
down you go
in this picture cosmology all of
cosmology
is as
a role
from up on the top of a potential
up here somewheres
down to the bottom
almost everything that we know about
almost everything we know about and
certainly everything we can observe
happened
after the universe plopped to the bottom
down here
okay
with the exception
of this exponential expansion
almost all of which in fact all of which
took place up on the top here
going over the edge
is where the vacuum energy was converted
into the energy of particles radiation
and other more familiar forms of energy
but not all of it
some little bit of it was left over as
vacuum energy
why
we don't know we don't know this is just
the picture that emerges from uh
from
lots and lots of detailed observation
so when
the big u
went over the edge of the hill here off
the edge of the cliff
that's the place where vacuum energy
this vacuum energy not this vacuum
energy here
but this big vacuum energy up here was
converted
into ordinary energy ordinary things
yeah including dark matter and other
things
i can't think of any known process so
that converts vacuum energy to
energy
this field
like any other field has quanta
associated with it when the field rolls
down to here and oscillates back and
forth
those quanta have energy
this is a kind of harmonic oscillator it
oscillates back and forth here the
energy of those harmonic oscillators is
another way of speaking about the quanta
the energy of the quanta of that field
so
when this field which is called the
inflicton it has a name once you name it
you no longer
ask why it exists you just say it's the
inflaton
the inflaton field
goes over the edge
and it starts ringing down here
it starts oscillating
those oscillations are another way of
talking about the particles the field
quanta
which are the field quanta associated
with this particular field
right
now those field quanta
may or may not be stable
if they were perfectly stable
that's all that would exist
there would be no way of transferring
that energy to other kinds of energy
but typically the situation with scalar
particles like the higgs particle or
other other scalar fields is they're
unstable
and they decay
so one of these particles forming
the sloshing stuff here let's call it
the inflaton can decay what can it decay
into who knows photons electrons
e plus e minus
and that's the way the energy gets
converted from the sloshing of this
inflaton field into ordinary
ordinary particles
now
do we know
enough about this field to say that this
must happen no but we know enough about
nature to say that it must happen
most of the energy in the universe is
composed of either dark matter or
one thing this could be
the sloshing around in here
which is a form of energy
could be the dark matter but we still
have to get some of it out into
photons and protons and neutrons and so
forth
so some decays of this type must have
happened
that's the only way to get it to
transfer
but uh
you know there's all kinds there's all
kinds of processes that can convert
this sloshing stuff into uh into
ordinary particles
so that's happening today the conversion
of
dark matter could be decaying if the if
in fact this is connected with dark
matter we don't know what dark matter is
with the precision
yeah that could be happening today
today in this picture
we're really stuck down at the bottom
here the sloshing ended but and i'm
going to if i get to it i'll show you
why the sloshing ended
so what we normally think of as
the vacuum energy
is really the residual
yeah
you think there's some kind of
there may be some connection between the
uv ir
connection and i don't know
let's get to let's get to an an
important point here
you might ask
if
well first of all if you started up on
the top here
and you fell over the edge
wouldn't you start
by energy conservation wouldn't you
swing back and forth here and perhaps
come back up onto the top
or at minimum wouldn't you expect to
endlessly swing back and forth here is
there any reason
why this energy would get degraded
as if there was dissipation
as if there were friction
which would cause this field to slide
down to the bottom
now think of a mechanical analogy the
mechanical analogy is a particle rolling
on a potential like this
why does it come to rest down here does
it come to rest down here the answer is
it better come to rest down here because
if it didn't our universe would be
filled with this enormous quantity of
energy and it's not it's pretty much
empty space
how did it get to be empty space where
did all that energy go
and i'm going to tell you it dissipated
and say what do you mean it dissipated
dissipated into what
well
there's a form of dissipation which
takes place in cosmology that doesn't
have to do with genuine friction it
resembles friction
very much
but
it is actually due to the expansion of
space so i thought i would take a couple
of minutes and show you where that comes
from
to do that
you'll have to recall something which
not everybody in the room
may know
but it's lagrange's equations of motion
this is the expression for an energy
let's suppose
that the field did not vary with
position in space just to make the story
simple
let's ignore
the gradients of the field with respect
to position and space
why because it's gotten itself stretched
out so much that this is unimportant
let's assume that's unimportant
all right this is the potential energy
this looks like a kinetic energy of
something
it's not the motion of a particle
but mathematically
it's proportional to the square of a
time derivative it looks like a kinetic
energy
of a degree of freedom which in this
case is a field and this looks like a
potential energy
what would be the lagrangian this would
be the energy what would be the
lagrangian of such a thing
energy is t plus v
lagrangian is t minus v t stands for
kinetic energy
so the lagrangian
so the lagrangian is t minus v
now actually this is not the lagrangian
this is the lagrange density
you have to multiply it by the volume of
space
this was not the potential energy this
was the potential energy density
to get the potential energy you have to
multiply it by the volume of space right
same here this was energy density
so what's the volume
of space
well
a cubed
a cubed of time
so now
if we know how a cube behaves with time
we have the lagrangian of this field
phi
okay let's work out its equation of
motion do you remember how to work out
the equation of motion for lagrangian
you take partial of l with respect to
phi dot
that's a
of t
cubed times phi dot
and then take the time derivative of
that that's the left hand side
what about the right hand side
anybody remember
dividify like a force like dv dx
like dv dx except there's the a cubed
here
a cubed
dv or dv defined
dvd phi is the slope
and it's the force term
which creates what would be an ordinary
acceleration if a was constant with time
but a is not constant with time so we
have a little bit of work to do
to take this derivative
to take the derivative what is the
derivative well the first term the d by
dt acts on the phi dot and that gives us
a cubed
times
phi double dot
which is like the acceleration not the
acceleration of the expansion of the
universe but it's just the acceleration
of this field phi the second time
derivative of phi
that's one term what's the other term
the other term comes from
differentiating the a cubed
and that's
three a squared of t
times what
times a dot
times phi dot
and that's equal to a cubed d v d phi
but i want to divide both sides of the
equation by a cubed just to get rid of
as many a cubed as i can
all right
so on the right hand side i'll just have
d v d phi
and on the left hand side i'll get rid
of this a cubed
i'll get rid of a squared
but
it will leave me with a 1 over a in the
denominator
so let's put 1 over a a dot over a
what do you what's a dot over a it's
another name for it
not the square root of h it's h
right
just h
so this is the hubble constant
now have you ever seen oh this is minus
this should be a minus here minus d v d
phi
uh
yeah minus t v d phi
force is proportional to minus the
derivative of the potential energy have
you ever seen an equation of motion with
a single phi dot in it like that
viscosity
a
ball or a rock falling through water
this is essentially the equation of
motion
of a rock falling through water here's
the gravitational force on it dvd phi
and it's proportional to the slope here
here's the acceleration
and here's the viscous drag force
here's the viscous drag force
so believe it or not this is called
hubble friction
hubble friction it's not real friction
it's due to the time dependence of the
size of the universe that's where it
came from it came from differentiating a
but it resembles very very closely
uh the equation of motion for an object
moving through a viscous fluid
and if v has a more or less uniform
slope
it's like a
object falling through a viscous fluid
in
under the presence of a uniform force
what happens under those circumstances
to the falling object
it comes to some terminal velocity
it comes to some terminal velocity very
quickly
when you drop a rock in the water and it
very quickly comes to terminal velocity
so the universe starts sliding down this
hill
if this is shallow enough it goes very
slowly down the hill here and as it goes
down the hill
the viscous
friction or hubble
viscosity or whatever it should be
called hubble
damping
brings it very quickly to a terminal
velocity and it just slides down this
hill slowly until it gets to the end
during the time that it's sliding down
the hill
or sliding down a hill which is a very
very shallow nature there's some vacuum
energy and that vacuum energy causes
almost exact exponential expansion
when i say almost exact it's not exactly
because there's some slope here so the
vacuum energy changes from one time to
another but if this is
reasonably flat
the universe will grow exponentially
approximately with a constant h here
and then it will come to the end and
fall down
and uh
how many times does the size of the
universe double
well that depends
on how shallow this is
how broad it is and how high it is
the height of it
goes into the coefficient here
goes into the time constant here
the width of it
and the slope of it determine just how
long it stays up on the top of the hill
there
so by making it broad enough
and flat enough
you can make the universe expand as many
times as you like during this period of
inflation
okay so then you would say
if it exponentiates by many many many
orders of magnitude
why doesn't that uh
why doesn't that make why doesn't that
iron out
all of the variation in the field
why does it have any variation at all
by the time it gets over the edge here
what is that variation that variation is
that small
little bit that's necessary for galaxies
to form so on the one hand you've
explained the flatness of the universe
and the homogeneity
but it looks as though you might have
overdone it you might have overdone it
and lost the possibility of explaining
the existence of galaxies
now marvelously
that's not exactly right
so
to understand why it's not exactly right
we have to have we have to take some
things from quantum mechanics
let's suppose that the universe was not
expanding
and
uh
just the simplest uh the simplest uh
possibility let's forget the expansion
of the universe for a moment
but let's add quantum mechanics to this
picture of a field
a field filling space
where the field
because of the expansion but we're going
to forget the expansion but because of
the expansion the field has gotten
extremely ironed out
so it's almost perfectly homogeneous
but
quantum mechanics makes it fluctuate
quantum mechanics makes it fluctuate one
way of seeing the fact that quantum
mechanics makes it fluctuate
is just by looking at the similarity
of the field
of its energy
plus v of phi
by looking at the similarity of such a
field with the motion of an ordinary
particle this is like kinetic energy and
there's some potential energy over here
plus another term over here
why is it it's kind of like a harmonic
oscillator this vfi
could conceivably be a harmonic
oscillator potential
but there's also a harmonic oscillator
potential in here hidden in here
why is it that harmonic oscillators have
zero point energy
they have zero point energy because of
the uncertainty principle
you cannot have
phi
being fixed and locked and at the same
time have the velocity of phi be fixed
and locked it's the uncertainty
principle
the uncertainty principle in the same
way that the uncertainty principle tells
you
that there's zero point energy of a
harmonic oscillator ground state energy
whatever it's called
the same mathematics
tells you that phi is necessarily even
in its ground state even when all the
energy is sucked out of it
it's still oscillating with zero point
energy
so that means if you were to look
microscopically at this field
you would see it constantly in a state
of agitation
even just in the state of absolutely
lowest energy
okay why don't why don't we notice those
fluctuations and for the most part we
don't notice them because they were too
rapid
they take place too rapidly for most for
most observations and we average over
them
okay we average over them
most such fluctuations are fairly short
wavelength and the short wavelengths
oscillate very fast and because they
oscillate fast we don't notice them but
in cosmology the situation is a little
bit different
and to understand how the situation is
different you have to take into account
the expansion of the universe that's the
main new thing the expansion of the
universe
okay let's draw the universe
horizontal is space as always
vertical is time
and
x goes horizontally
x is the coordinate x it doesn't measure
distance
it measures coordinate along here
here are the various galaxies for
example
i'm putting them equally spaced which of
course they're not
and of course the world is
three-dimensional not one-dimensional
but these are the galaxies i've
approximated them by saying they're
equally spaced and they're just vertical
lines
but the distance between galaxies is not
the difference in x but what is it
ax
a being scale factor
so distance
is a of t
times delta x
where delta x might be the distance in
coordinate between two points
so if a is x
let's imagine now that a is
exponentially expanding e to the ht
times delta x
that means the distance between galaxies
on the average
if they're far enough apart
is expanding exponentially
delta x is of course not expanding
exponentially delta x is just the fixed
coordinate positions of the galaxies
you can think of it as their names
but it's the scale factor which is
increasing exponentially now what
happens to a wave in here
happens to a typical wave
as the universe expands
it gets stretched out but in these
coordinates it's not stretched in these
coordinates it stays more or less the
same with time
it has a fixed wavelength in x
but that means an exponentially growing
wavelength
in proper distance the proper distance
so the wave
more or less has the same profile it may
be oscillating
but it's not expanding
on this diagram
because this diagram already has the
expansion built in
as the expansion of the distance between
these points
okay but it oscillates the field
oscillates
in general it oscillates
unless its wavelength is too too long
if its wavelength is too long it doesn't
oscillate so let me explain why it
doesn't oscillate
um supposing we have why does a wave why
does a wave oscillate first of all why
does an ordinary electromagnetic wave
oscillate
think of a
rope stretched between two points
and perhaps the rope has some curvature
over here
maybe it does maybe it doesn't
let's just
may have some curvature may not
why does the rope over here get pulled
down
it gets pulled down by its neighbors by
the neighboring segments of rope
which would typically be down
here what if the neighboring segment of
rope was up here
which way would it get pulled
up
all right
so the only way to know which way it's
going to get pulled is to know what the
neighbors are doing
in particular
well yes to know what the neighborhood
what the neighbors are doing
but supposing
the size of the wave here
was about as big as the horizon
as about as big as the horizon remember
what the horizon is the horizon is
distance
beyond which things are moving away from
you
faster than the speed of light
you can never get any information from
beyond the horizon
that's a principle
nothing can communicate from behind the
horizon
so here's a piece of rope
that if the scale is big enough for the
variation of the position of the rope
one could imagine
that
that this piece of rope is out beyond
the horizon
supposing this piece of rope was out
beyond the horizon can it have any
influence on this piece no
no so it better be
that the tendency to pull on this piece
of rope
or this piece of field this little piece
of field in here
that had better get be
tremendously diminished
when the wavelength of the wave
becomes about equal
to the size of the horizon
when the wavelength is longer than the
size of the horizon
then the pieces which are pulling on a
piece over here
are out beyond the horizon
and the answer is if you follow the
mathematics
that when waves get longer wavelength
than the size of the horizon they freeze
they're not pulled back by the neighbors
and they just freeze their motion
becomes frozen
all right why should i worry about waves
i'm worried now i'm worried about
quantum fields my goodness what are we
talking about waves longer than the size
of the horizon
well
the point is
that the universe is expanding so take a
wave of a certain wavelength
and push it ahead in time
on this graph it has the same wavelength
but the distance between these points
exponentially grows
so no matter how small the wavelength is
to start with
eventually as the universe grows and
stretches
each
hidden wave each zero point oscillation
will eventually have a wavelength longer
than the size of the horizon
when that happens the wave stops
oscillating
it just stops oscillating it is no
longer pulled back and it freezes it
just freezes
so if we wait long enough let's suppose
this wavelength here is um
i don't know 10 to the minus eight
centimeters some small wavelength and
it's oscillating like mad because it's
being pulled back into place by its
neighbors
but as time goes on this 10 to the minus
eight centimeters
grows to the point
where it may be as big as the horizon
will be as big as the horizon when that
happens
all of a sudden the wave freezes so the
zero point also in an expanding universe
an exponentially expanding universe
the zero point oscillations become
frozen
first the longer wavelength ones become
all right so eventually
this wave over here will become frozen
but then what about shorter wavelengths
shorter wavelengths
will take a longer time
but they will also eventually become
frozen
even the very shortest wavelengths that
you can imagine
will eventually become frozen yeah if
you do the horizon distance from your
origin on that graph would it kind of
asymptotically go to the vertical axis
yeah that's a good point all right so
let's draw what the horizon would look
like
the horizon what is the horizon the
horizon let's let's work out what the
size of the horizon the horizon is a
distance
that corresponds to the speed of light
using the hubble formula
all right so it's uh velocity
sorry um
distance i always have
i always have to work this out distance
is uh sorry velocity is equal to hubble
times distance
um
the place the distance at which uh this
is the speed of light that's called the
horizon and that distance therefore is
the speed of light
divided by the hubble constant
that's the distance that corresponds to
the distance to the
horizon right so that's the distance
they go what did you ask me you asked me
a question
oh yeah
right right yeah yes yes it does
uh the distance
is a fixed number the distance to the
horizon is fixed it's just c over h and
in an exponentially expanding universe h
is fixed
all right but the distances on this
graph
are exponentially increasing
so a fixed distance on this graph looks
smaller and smaller
a fixed distance
of hubble size
this is called hubble size this distance
here
would look smaller and smaller because
it's being compared with exponentially
growing distances
so that means
that the
horizon size
would look like this
exponentially getting smaller and
smaller with time
and that's why each wave
will eventually
it's frozen
and in uh becomes frozen
when its wavelength gets longer than the
horizon size
okay
or when the horizon in coordinate
distance is shrunken to be smaller than
the uh
right
okay so each wave gets frozen
and they pile up on top of each other
they pile up on top of each other each
one frozen
and what was originally quantum
fluctuations very rapidly oscillating
become
large-scale fluctuations of the field
which grow
and which pile up on top of each other
and which just freeze
at the end of this
by the time you get to here
all these waves are piled up and made
some sort of variation in the field some
sort of frozen variation in the field
and so the next question is
when this field which now varies from
notice notice it does not matter
how long it's been inflating
it could have been inflating
so long that the universe is 10 to the
10 to the 10 to the 10 to the 10 would
go on all night that's how that's how
much bigger it is that's how much it
would be ironed out but nevertheless as
time goes on
new fluctuations get frozen
new waves become frozen more and more of
them become frozen
and so the end result is there's always
a variation that's kind of a fossil
remnant
of early vacuum fluctuations that got
frozen into the system
and they get frozen in pile up on top of
each other and become a large-scale
massive macroscopic uh variation of the
field yeah
what happens what
is
yeah it's scaling down it's diluting at
the same time it's energy density is
diluting as it expands so in fact i mean
it doesn't get it doesn't get out of
control from the point of view of energy
density
but it just keeps making you know
more oscillations top piled up on some
more oscillations
uh and the effect is a kind of
stationary steady state uh
variation that's
that's yeah that's what it's going to
ask you you get to a steady state where
the
where as time goes on you erase
the earlier well you stretch them out
you stretch them out
and new ones keep coming in right right
you stretch them out so that they're
bigger than the horizon you look at it
at one time and look at it
two hours later or two years or whatever
else right it looks the same right
that's called a scale invariant
spectrum
scale and variance spectrum and one of
the things that has been known about the
initially you said it seemed something
like you're saying that the older
fluctuations were occupied by being
frozen right
but it sounds like what you're really
saying is they were ossified first
not only were they occupied they were
spread out
they were ossified and then stretched
but they're not seen as fluctuations or
because the wavelength is so long
i mean okay remember there was the
horizon
two let's there were two different
horizon scales there was the horizon
up here and there's the horizon down
here
the horizon up here just means the
distance scale associated with the
vacuum energy in here
okay
the hubble scale down here means the
distance scale associated with this
energy density
they're very different
right a small horizon up here
right these waves become ossified when
they move
during this era the waves get ossified
when they get bigger
than the horizon associated with this
energy scale this could be some
microscopically small thing from our
point of view
right then they get frozen peanuts
fluctuations even though they're frozen
they're frozen
at a point where it's actually far far
enough away that when we get a smoke our
horizons
that's right that's right our horizon
grows what happens at first
is that these waves get bigger than the
temporary
it's really a false horizon but a
temporary horizon over here
but then the horizon grows
when it rolls down here the horizon
suddenly turns that way
and these waves come back into the
horizon and they start to oscillate
again
they start to fluctuate again
but by that time they're stretched out
on enormously large scales
and they're piled up
so you have a huge pile up of waves
macroscopic
structures
and those macroscopic structures
um
start to slosh around again
in fact that's really what happens they
the words we use is they go out of the
horizon and come back into the horizon
so they
expand out beyond
this temporary horizon and then get
swallowed up
by the larger horizon at which point
they start to slush around again
right
but
as i said by the time they start
sloshing around again they're big
macroscopic um
uh
right and take a long time to swing
occurred in really a very small amount
of time well we don't know how long
well
let's just say
last week like you said it might be 60
people oh that would be very very small
amounts of time i mean by microscopic
standards yes very very strong
how did
i don't know if you can answer this in
the timing name but how did you
calculate the power spectrum that you
get
well just from this picture just just
from this picture that the waves keep
different wavelengths
keep passing out of the horizon
but at each stage the same thing is
happening exactly the same thing is
happening as the previous stage
and it's on a logarithmic scale one can
calculate it and see that at each stage
it looks the same
except everything scaled up and
it reaches this sort of stationary
phase that's so that's a little too
complicated to go into but it does it
does achieve this scale and variant
behavior where the same more or less the
same amplitude of oscillation for every
wavelength that's not exactly true but
uh
[Music]
but close to it
and the result is a
particular structure of frozen in
oscillate frozen in density variations
okay now let's let's go a little bit
further
and talk about what happens when you go
over the edge here
when you go over the edge
those fluctuations get magnified not
magnified in spatial size
but magnified in
amplitude or in energy density
the energy density the energy variation
from place to place gets magnified
and it gets magnified proportional
or inversely proportional
to how slowly the field no
inversely proportional to how fast the
field was rolling down here
the flatter it is
the smaller the terminal velocity as
it's rolling down here
the smaller the terminal velocity
you might think this is a little bit
counter-intuitive but the smaller the
terminal velocity
the bigger
the variation in the energy density will
be
after you fall off the edge here
so let me just show you why that is i
talked about it a little bit last time
i was a little bit tired last time
so let me just say a little bit more
about it
okay so the field is varying from place
to place because of these quantum
fluctuations
let's say to the right
is red and to the left is blue then
there will be regions which are redder
regions which are
let me use green
here's green
back here
and red over here
so there will be greener regions and red
regions and green regions and red
regions
now
i don't really mean
back here and up here i just mean small
deviations from here to here
small small fluctuations
this uh it's not this is a an effect
that has to be fairly small
otherwise it would have created too much
random mess in the universe
so it's a small effect
but there are greener regions slightly
to the left and redder regions to
slightly to the right
naturally the redder regions fall off
the edge before the greener regions
okay
supposing a little red region over here
falls off the edge of the cliff
it falls off the edge of the cliff and
all of this
vacuum energy
let's suppose all of it for simplicity
all of it got converted to radiation
energy that's a simple mod that's a
simplified story but let's suppose it
just got all turned into uh photons and
so forth
so let's see the redder region after
because it was a little bit ahead
it was a little bit of head moving
toward the edge of the cliff it got
there first
and fell off the edge so this redder
region
would have
all of its energy
turned into
a kind of energy
which dilutes with expansion
the greener energy which is still up on
the top here is still vacuum energy it
does not dilute
okay
so what happens to the energy density in
here
the energy density in there decreases
it decreases
just by the standard rules by the time
you're down off this cliff
you're in a world now which is pretty
much like ordinary cosmology
ordinary material
radiation or whatever
if it were radiation we know the energy
density in there would go as one over a
to the fourth
the scale factor in that region or the
expansion factor in that region would be
growing
and the effect would be that the energy
density in there decreased
okay what about the energy density in
the greener region after it fell off the
edge of the cliff
it would be higher because it fell off
later
so
by the time
a bit of green energy goes over the edge
the red energy has already been
red-shifted
it has already been red-shifted or
diluted by expansion
whereas the greener regions
are
not yet diluted
but if you wait a little more
the redder regions will get even more
diluted the green region will start to
get diluted
and the even greener region will come
and fall over the edge and make a yet
higher energy density region
this is the way that
oh
and what is this effect proportional to
well the slower the average motion
the longer the time scale
between
different pieces falling over the edge
if everything is moving extremely slowly
even if one point is slightly ahead of
the other here
if it's moving extremely slowly
there will be a large gap in time
between the time the first piece rolls
off and time the second piece rolls off
that means
that the red energy will get highly
diluted by the time the green energy
falls off so the flatter this is
and the slower it moves
the larger will be the variations in the
energy density from place to place
the final upshot is a spectrum of
fluctuations of energy density
which is the remnant of all of this
which depends it depends on the height
of this
it depends on the doesn't depend much on
the width but it depends on the slope a
little bit why the slope
because the terminal velocity depends on
the slope and the slower the terminal
velocity
the bigger will be the fluctuations
doesn't depend much on the width
so for that reason we can't say how many
e foldings took place
but it depends on the height
and the slope
in such a way that the shallower the
slope the bigger the fluctuations
also the higher it is the bigger the
fluctuations
the higher it is the more energy density
the larger will be the fluctuations and
the flatter and there's a formula that
you can work out
that will tell you how big the
fluctuations are
but the point is
that
the detailed result of such an analysis
fits extremely well
with uh
with empirical data
no unfortunately you cannot tell what
the heightened slope is you can only
tell a combination of the height in the
slope
there's one combination of the height
and the slope that uh that you can
predict
okay
and uh
well okay
that's not quite true
okay not quite true
um
if the height is high enough
then
there are in addition to the production
of these density fluctuations there are
production during the gravitational era
here or during this inflationary era
there are also gravitational waves
produced
and so
ad mixed into this
density fluctuation and the temperature
fluctuation on the sky
there may be also gravitational waves
that are visible
if there are gravitational waves that
will tell us how high it is
but if it's too low
then there won't be visible
gravitational waves and that's possibly
the case very likely the case
so it's going to wait until uh the
gravitational waves can be detected
from this period and that will give us
some idea of how high it is most likely
it will just tell us it's lower than a
certain amount
if the energy density were any bigger
i'll tell you the
if
in plunk units and plunk units
if the energy density were bigger than
about 10 to the minus 14th
which may sound small but it's a huge
energy density
bigger than about 10 to the minus 14th
then we would have already been swamped
by gravitational waves from it
so we know that the energy density is
less than 10 to the minus 14th because
we were not swamped by gravitational
waves
on the other hand if it's less than
about 10 to the minus 16th then we have
no chance of seeing the gravitational
waves and so there's a narrow little
window which we have no reason to
believe is uh
[Music]
something like that i think
um narrow little window where you could
see gravitational waves
10 to the minus minus 14 might actually
be 10 to the minus 2 i don't remember
the precise numbers but it's in that
ballpark
um
there's only a narrow region of
parameter space where you could see
these
units
of mass over pike volume
is that what we refer to 10 minus 6 and
16 what
mass to the fourth
yeah why is it mass to the fourth so let
me explain why it's mass to the fourth
first of all
um
if you set c equal to one and h-bar
equal to one those are those are natural
things to do
then
mass is the same as inverse length
all right mass is the same as inverse
length so let's just the mass and
inverse length are the same thing
what did you ask me i forgot
oh what are the units of uh
of the energy all right it's energy
density first of all
energy density so it's energy
divided by length cubed
and if one over length is the same as
energy then it's energy to the fourth
okay
so it's m plunk to the fourth that uh
the units
right and uh
and empirically we know from the lack of
gravitational waves in the spectrum of
uh
in the cosmic
background spectrum that
it's less than maybe it's 10 to the
minus 12 i don't remember exactly but uh
and the problem is
that if it was another decade or two
smaller than that you would have no
chance of seeing it so you're caught
between
uh
being swamped by it
well you're not swamped by it and in a
couple of decades down and you couldn't
see
it might
mean cosmology
oh yeah yeah we would have seen we would
have seen a lot more structure in the uh
in the microwave background
yeah
yeah due to the success of freezing out
of these long waves and fly shouldn't ty
be undergoing a random walk
yeah it does undergo a random walk at
any point at any point that undergoes a
random walk it's exactly what it does
but of course it undergoes different
random walks at different places and
that's what makes the variation
yeah it's a statistical process that's
exactly right
so if you if you focused on one
particular point in space
you would see one mode freeze out then
the next mode frees out the next mode
freeze out with random phase between
them
and it would make a random walk that's
exactly right
so the question that preoccupied people
for a long time which is what happened
at
is irrelevant there is not equal there
well irrelevant or not well
okay so the
right the well let's put it this way
the success of this theory and has been
highly successful in correlating a lot
of data
on different wavelength scales when i
say it correlates lots of data
it correlates data about fluctuations on
very different scales
scales comparable to the whole size of
the sky variations across the sky which
are which are
large scale down to very small scales of
a thousand times smaller than the size
of the whole sky and it correlates all
those fluctuations density fluctuations
basically into one
set of parameters governing this
potential here so in that sense it's
highly successful
the upside of it is it washes out
whatever the initial conditions were
because this stretching
washes out what came before and only the
quantum fluctuations which are produced
later
are relevant
so the success of it
is that it washes out what came before
uh
but what's one error's success becomes
another errors disaster
it means now that we accept all of this
and we all think it's true
next thing we want to know is what
happens earlier
and
all of the things which made this a very
successful theory work against us in
finding out what happened earlier
so inflation when it occurs
tends to wipe out the past
and as i said that's both good and bad
particularly bad for those who want to
understand what might have
led up to this this is a the point is
this is a ridiculous starting point
this energy density
while
it's easy to accept that the universe
might have started with a very high
energy density
that's easy to accept big deal
um
the problem is
the energy density was very very high
in ordinary units joules per cubic meter
or whatever it was enormously high
energy even on particle scale units
much higher energy density than for
example the density of energy inside a
proton
so it was enormously high energy
on the other hand it was very small in
any natural units
it was 10 to the minus 14 or something
or 10 to the minus 12 or smaller so it's
neither here nor there so to speak it's
neither
very big nor very small it doesn't sound
like it's the sort of place
that natural starting point would be
natural starting point might be with the
energy density for example being
plunkian
being one unit in plank units 10 to the
minus 13 or 10 to the minus 14 doesn't
sound like it's the starting point no of
course it could be wrong i don't know
but there's no natural
explanation
of this whole structure
and why we might have started over here
and whether or not we might have tumbled
down from some much much higher energy
density up here
that's all lost
that's all experimentally lost
because
inflation just stretched things out so
much that we lost it could be that there
was no starting
could the exponential have gone on you
mean into the remote past
no
no this is an extremely odd story
um
you say what would have happened
if the energy density was absolutely
constant out here for example well this
function has to do something
right
it could increase in this manner here
in which case it would say in the remote
past something different was happening
than down here
okay
exactly what was it well we then go up
to here and we say could there have been
a plateau up here that went on and on
indefinitely
well we might as well say could there
have been a plateau over here that went
on indefinitely
all right so what are the consequences
then of a
universe
with an absolutely constant energy
density like this let's suppose we're
way out here with an absolutely constant
energy density
well when i s the i told you that the
sitter space was an exponentially
expanding universe
that is
correct at late times
in fact real the sitter space
is a universe
which looks like this
which contracts and then expands
that's the real honest solution of
einstein's equations with a cosmological
constant
it contracts and then it expands
it contracts to some minimum size
the minimum size happens to be the
hubble scale
and then it starts expanding
and it expands exponentially
i wrote that
i wrote the um
that the
the scale factor
was like the exponential of h t
that's not exactly right can you think
of a function which contracts and then
expands and uh and the late times looks
like exponential hyperbolic hyperbolic
cosh
yeah kosh
ht that's the real solution of
einstein's equations
so the real solution of einstein's
equations
is not an eternally exponentially
expanding universe but it's one which
contracts and expands
now should we believe the question comes
up should we believe in this contracting
phase
all right should we believe in the
contracting phase that came before the
expansion i will just leave that as a
question mark
uh
i will leave that as a question mark
or should we believe
that somehow we started
in some other way
unknown i think mr i think that mystery
down here we don't know very much about
that
we really don't have a theory of the
beginnings
um
if
this plateau really gave way to a much
higher mountain here
it would mean
that this might have started much
smaller
in fact if it gave way to a mountain
which is as high as the plunk scale we
might even want to say it started as the
smallest possible thing one plunk length
on the side
the fact is we don't know
we don't know very much about any of
this
no no why did he say that
because it's all erased it seems well
can't see it
just means you have to be clever
yeah it's of course all erased
if there was too many e foldings
right
if we are very very lucky and there were
63 foldings then we have a chance of
seeing it
we have a chance of seeing some of this
um
[Applause]
i'm trying to think out what the uh
level damping
does to
the field equations
in particular
does that change the quanta
of the field equations as time goes on
what it is
is it's the redshifting of the field
quanta it's equivalent to the
redshifting of the field quanta
in other words it appears that energy is
being lost
but one way of thinking about it
is uh the energy is just being stretched
so it's completely equivalent to the
redshifting
so
you mentioned in passing that
the units the units of length and mass
are inverse to each other
the formula for example for the compton
what's the formula for the compton
wavelength
a quantum mechanical wavelength of a
particle of mass m
compton wavelength lambda compton
anybody know
it's got an h-bar in it
it's quantum mechanical
well
all the momentum
but
we're talking about now a particle of a
given mass
so it has to have units of mass times
velocity
m times c
h bar over m c is the comp in wavelength
so we know that h bar over m c has units
of a length
now
if we work in units in which c is one
which we've all gotten very used to by
now
and if we're also
quantum mechanically inclined we might
also
set h-bar equal to one we don't have to
we can just say that lambda is inverse
to a mass but if we do set h-bar equal
to one which is a common thing to do
then
wavelength has units of one over mass so
length has units of one over mass masses
units of one over length
uh
when these waves get stretched out and
they become frozen their frequency goes
to zero obviously so wouldn't that mean
yes
continually
as this process goes on
waves
become frozen
they become stretched
their energy is degraded and they're
replaced by new ones
but the net effect as it was pointed out
was a kind of random walk
where the field just becomes a
statistical noisy mess
and on every scale and every length
scale
so what's depleted by the expansion gets
replaced by uh
by new waves coming in and uh
and freezing in on top of those previous
ones
is that like the slowing down of uh
coordinate time when you approach an
event horizon
which
well like when you approach your event
horizon of a black hole yeah
you got more and more red shifting
of how probable inflation was
in a sense of looking at
various parameters for the
yeah
yeah there's a space of parameters
the first order
not first order in any technical sense
but the first order in
thinking about it
is the width of this
there's the height of it
and there's a slope of it
the slope
remember the slope comes in in a
prominent way
because the slower the the smaller the
slope the slower the field moves and the
slower it moves the more
the bigger the fluctuations
these are three parameters
the height let's call it v naught the
height of it
uh the slope of it
and the width of it i don't know delta
phi
now
um generally speaking most physicists
are of the opinion
delta phi incidentally has units and it
has units of mass
generally speaking physicists get very
uncomfortable when a thing with the unit
of mass gets bigger fundamental thing
becomes bigger in mass than the plunk
mass you're very uncomfortable about
that
and most of us would probably maintain
that the
scale of variation of a field like phi
should never be bigger than about one
unit in planck mass that may or may not
be true
but if it's true it tells us one piece
of information
another piece of information is that the
energy density should never be bigger
than one in planck units that's
something we really believe
i won't get into the reasons for it but
that's there's a lot of reason for that
and so
having some kind of bounds on these
we're really talking about bound on the
slope here we're talking about what's
the probability
that the slope is shallow enough
that 62e foldings happen or 60 e
foldings happen
what's the probability and the answer is
about two percent
that you have to adjust this slope to
in order to get it to roll slowly enough
here
to get the required number of e-foldings
all right is two percent uh
is that how how unlikely or how likely
is that
well
um
it's two percent
now there's another interesting element
to it there is another but i won't have
time for it so i i'm not going to try to
get into it there is another element to
it
uh the other element well no no
uh the question is is inflation
we would need to get into issues of
anthropic uh
questions
we have two puzzles cosmological puzzles
both of them are fine-tuning puzzles
one of them is a mild fine-tuning it's
only two percent in some way of thinking
about it
um
it's it's only two percent
the other is the fine tuning of this 10
to the minus 123 down here
the two big fine-tuning puzzles both of
them
can be resolved in one
simple
explanation
whether you like it or not
that the universe had to be such
that structure formed in it structure
meaning galaxy stars planets and so
forth
and here's a way to think about it
um
a positive cosmological let's let's take
uh let's take a particular case positive
cosmological constant
and open
negatively curved universe let's take
that as our model
we could take any other combination we
like we get the same answer but let's
take positive cosmological constant in
open universe
okay so what is a
positive cosmological constant from a
newtonian point of view
from a newtonian point of view it's a
repulsion
it's a repulsion a repulsive force a
universal repulsive force which is
proportional to distance
that's what a cosmological constant is
if we went back to the newtonian
description of things
that we started with in the very early
part of the quarter
and added in to the usual newtonian
gravitational force between objects
another term
which was proportional to a thing called
lambda
times the distance between objects
that would mimic the cosmological
constant and a positive cosmological
constant which is what we see
we correspond to a universal repulsion
but because it increases as a function
of distance
it had better be small
it better be small enough that it
doesn't affect the solar system
in fact it better be small enough that
it doesn't affect the galaxy
it doesn't affect seriously big clusters
of galaxies
and in fact experimentally it's known to
only be important at the scale of that
10 billion light years
so it's a very small repulsion
but what would happen if it was 100
times bigger 10 to the minus 123 is how
big it is
right it's because it's so small that it
only has an effect on
incidentally what if it was 10 to the
minus 10
that repulsion yeah it would be easily
enough to blow apart an electron
what if it was 10 to the minus 100
easily big enough to blow the earth out
of just uh oh easily easily by many
orders of magnitude
right
so
what if it was 10 to the minus 121
instead of 10 to the minus 123
well not galaxies today it would not be
potent enough to blow up the galaxies
today but it would be potent enough
to prevent this
one part and ten to the five
fluctuations from condensing into
galaxies
so this very mild variation that was
there left over from inflation
uh
it would only take a little bit of
universal repulsive cosmological
constant
term
to prevent it from condensing into
galaxies this was weinberg stephen
weinberg's uh discovery in 1987
that a cosmological constant
roughly
two orders of magnitude bigger than the
10 to the minus 123
would have prevented galaxies from
forming
uh
at the time it was thought that the
cosmological constant was zero and he
said no there's no reason for that
whether it just has to be small enough
to allow galaxies to form
and he was right that experimentally it
wasn't zero
it was just small enough to allow
galaxies to form
okay there's a similar logic that goes
with the curvature of the universe
let's take the case of negative
curvature
do you remember what
k means from the newtonian point of view
or in particular k being whether you're
positive negatively or zero curved
it had to do with the energy of uh
recession
escape velocity k equals zero meant
everything is moving with exactly the
escape velocity
k
greater than zero
would mean
k greater than zero means less than the
escape velocity k less than zero means
greater than this so if we take the case
of k less than zero
which for one reason or another has
become the favored case but it wouldn't
really matter
if k were less than zero it would mean
that everything was shot out with
greater than the escape velocity
okay
well
that sounds bad it sounds like too much
velocity can also prevent galaxies from
forming
two things can prevent a rock which are
going out
from returning
one of them is if you're above the
escape velocity the other would be an
additional outward force that you didn't
know about which might have been
proportional to distance but very small
okay
um
both the cosmo both the positive
cosmological constant
and
negative curvature
would both work in the direction
of preventing
galaxies from forming
now
the cosmological constant is very small
what about the negative possibility of
negative curvature
if the universe is slightly negatively
curved today it was much more negatively
curved in the past
right because curvature radius of
curvature gets smaller so it's much more
negatively curved in the past
we go back to the past when galaxies
form and we say the universe must have
not been too negatively curved
what could have caused it not to be
negatively curved
if it started out negatively curved
what can dilute
curvature
expansion curvature yeah inflation
inflation
all right so you can say
how many e-foldings of inflation had to
take place
in order that the universe flattened
itself out enough
before this arrow and structure was
formed
how many e foldings had to have taken
place
in order that the outward thrust of
things didn't prevent galaxies from
forming
and the answer is about
59.5 e foldings
we know that there was at least 62
we know that for us to be here it had to
be more than 16 59.5
all right
so one explanation then
is that
we can just throw away the possibility
that there was less than 59.5 e foldings
and then we can ask the conditional
probability
what's the probability given that we're
here to ask the question in other words
given that there were more than 59.5 e
foldings then we can ask what's the
probability that there was more than 62
in other words we can take this
parameter space
and we can say let's cut out all the
parts of it
where there weren't enough e-foldings
enough expansion
to get rid of the large outward thrust
which would prevent galaxies from
forming
throw it away and ask with the remaining
part of the parameter space
given that there were more than 62 e
fold more than 59 e foldings what's the
probability that there was more than 62
and then the answer becomes maybe 0.9 or
something
so it depends on how you ask the
question what the probability of
inflation was if you ask the question
conditional that we're here to ask a
question
then the answer is that's very probable
if you ask the question from a more a
priori point of view what's the volume
in the parameter space
then it's less than two percent
so it depends on how you ask the
question the same is true for the
cosmological constant if you ask what's
the a priori probability that a number
is less than 10 to the minus 123 well
it's 10 to the minus 123.
but what's the probability that uh
that if we're here
then the number becomes of order one so
these are the great puzzles these are
the great confusions the great puzzles
the great debates which are going on
and that brings us to the end of the
great debate
[Applause]
[Music]
you